Fatih Sayin

Austin, TX 78729 | (512) 765 3221 | fmsayin@hotmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatih-sayin/ GitHub: https://github.com/fmsayin | Portfolio: https://fmsayin.github.io

CAREER SUMMARY

I am a strategic and multidisciplinary data analyst and professor in research methodology and theory with 10 years of experience in colleges. I worked as a school principal, university department chair and secretary general for 5 years earlier in my career. I combined my 15 years of expertise in research methodology, project management, and administrative experience with creative data analytics methods and gathered the best results. Major skills and expertise: Has an eye for innovation and analytical perfection. Collects, cleans, analyzes, visualizes, stores, and makes meaningful highlights out of the data with the best tools available. Proactively perfects skill sets and deepens experience with the tools VBA, Python, SQL, HTML, CSS, MongoDB, JavaScript, D3.js, Tableau, and Hadoop.

RELATED SKILLS

- Used fuzzy logic approach for hypothesis testing to validate data and interpretations
- Proposed solutions to improve system efficiencies and reduce total expenses
- Presented data and analysis in order to improve strategies and operations in academic institutions
- Performed data-driven cultural research to highlight nuances between the general and target business
- Detail-oriented, thorough, initiative, solution-seeker, enthusiastic-friendly team member, and excellent in understanding collaborative project-management to achieve high demands.

EDUCATION

The University of Texas at Austin | Data Analytics and Visualization Graduated in 2019

Ivane Javakhishvili State University, Tbilisi, Georgia | Ph.D. in International Relations Graduated in 2009

Free University of Tbilisi, Georgia | BA in International Relations Graduated in 2000

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Advanced Excel Functions: Pivot Tables, VBA Scripting
- Fundamental Statistics: Modeling, Forecasting
- Python Programming: Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, API Interactions
- Databases: SQL, MongoDB, SQLite and SqlAlchemy
- Web Visualization: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Dashboarding, JavaScript, D3.js, Leaflet.j, Tableau, and Hadoop.

MOST RECENT PROJECTS

- 1. Project
- Name: Trends in Austin Crime Data by Zip Code
- Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- **Description:** The city of Austin provides lots of interesting local data sets. We interested in crime data. Base on the data, zip code was the best geographic measure, but also wanted to use demographic data from the Census. We tried to describe each zip code base on four socio-economic indicators: income level, educational attainment, poverty level, unemployment rate.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/GROUP-PROJECT-Trends-in-Austin-crime-data-by-zip-code

Prezi Link: https://prezi.com/view/46V1XovwTPcJulr4D0rN/ (for project presentation)

- 2. Project
- Name: European Soccer League Analysis (EuroLeague)
- Tools Used: ETL, Python, Numpy, Pandas, Jupyter, SQLite, mySQL, SQLAlchemy
- **Description:** Euro Leagues and cities have very interesting data sets. So that we are interested in 28 European countries and cities GDP and these cities soccer team attitude data set. Base on the data, teams' success and cities GDP was the best measure for analysis. We tried to describe each team's success and players' attitude base on city income level.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/ETL-Project-EuroLeague

MOST RECENT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

1. Name: Heroes of Pymoli

- Tools Used: Python, Pandas, Jupyter Notebook.
- Programmed a general python script to analyze the data for a fantasy game. Generated a report that breaks down
 the game's purchasing data into meaningful insights.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Heroes of Pymoli

2. The World Cities Weather vs Latitude

- Tools Used: Python, API Interactions, Numpy, Matplotlib
- Coded a weather API python general script for over randomly selected 500 + cities across the world of varying distance from the equator to detect their temperature, humidity, cloudiness, and wind speed based on their latitude.

 Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Weather-Py

3. Rental Movie Database (Sakila)

- Tools Used: MySQL, GitHub
- Formulated a query to program total sales by each store and staff by type of the movies. Most frequently rented movies, top genres of movies that were detected.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/mysql_challange

4. Name: VBA of Wall Street

- Tools Used: VBA, Advanced Excel, GitHub
- Analyzed Wall Street stock market data in VBA script language.
 Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/The VBA of Wall Street

5. Kick Start Campaign: The Most Successful Start-Up Projects

- Tools Used: Advanced Excel, Pivot Tables
- Diagnosed and analyzed a database of 4,000 past projects in order to uncover any hidden trends for being a successful or unsuccessful Kick Start Campaign.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/advanced_excel

6. Web-Visualization

- Tools Used: Bootstrap, HTML and CSS
- This is an analysis and visualization of weather of 500+ cities across the world. The main objective was to showcase the relationship of various factors like temperature, humidity, cloudiness and wind speed with respect to the distance from the equator.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Web-Visualization.github.io

7. UFO Sightings: Automatic Table and Data Search

- Tools Used: JavaScript, HTML, CSS
- Wrote a code that creates a table dynamically based upon the dataset collected. Users to search through the table for specific pieces of information.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/UFO-sightings-JavaScript-and-DOM-Manipulation

8. Belly-Button Biodiversity: Bacteria Dashboard

- Tools Used: JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Flask API, SQLite, Heroku
- Used Flask to design an API for the dataset and to serve the HTML and JavaScript required for the dashboard
 page. SQLite database file and inside of the Flask application code was used for the database as JSON file format,
 and uploaded Herokuapp.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Belly-Button-Biodiversity-Plotly-

9. Data Journalism and D3

Sep 2009 – Jul 2011

Jul 2007 – Aug 2009

- Tools Used: JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, D3
- Used d3 techniques to create a scatter plot that represents each state with circle elements. The data was pulled from the Census Bureau. The series of features about the health risks facing particular demographics were put on an interactive map of d3.

Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Data-Journalism-and-D3/tree/master/Instructions

10. Earthquakes Visualization with Leaflet

- Tools Used: JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, D3, Leaflet
- Used JavaScript API calls for a real time Geo JSON earthquakes dataset and served to the HTML web application. Link: https://github.com/fmsayin/Earthquakes-Visualization-With-Leaflet

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE	
Jan 2019 – Present	Investment Consultant and Data Analyst, Cosmos Trading Inc. Austin, Texas, USA
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Researcher The University of Texas Austin / Huston – Tillotson University Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Adviser to the President (in Academics and Investment) Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2014 – Jul 2016	Founding Director of The Alliance of Civilizations Research Center
- -	Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Department Chair Department of International Trade and Business Administration and
	IR Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey
Jun 2009 – Jul 2011	Secretary General, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia
Jul 2007 – May 2009	Department Chair of Social Activities, International Black Sea University,
	Tbilisi, Georgia
Jul 2006 – Jun 2007	Founding Principal, Nikoloz Tsereteli International School, Tbilisi, Georgia
Jul 2004 – Jun 2006	Founding Principal, Niko Nikoladze Secondary School, Kutaisi, Georgia
	ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE
Oct 2018 – Present	Data Analytics and Visualization Boot Camp, The University of Texas at Austin
Aug 2016 – Sep 2018	Freelance Researcher The University of Texas Austin / Huston - Tillotson University,
	Austin, Texas, USA
Sep 2012 – Jul 2016	Assistant Professor, Department of International Trade and Business Administration and
	IR Canik Basari University, Samsun, Turkey

Lecturer, International Black Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia

Sea University, Tbilisi, Georgia

Assistant Professor, Department of Business Administration, International Black

PUBLICATIONS

I have published 19 articles in peer review journals. My academic work includes several articles about the European Union, Caucasus, and Euro -Asia which are published in internationally recognized research journals. I edited the Dictionary of Georgian -Turkish / Turkish-Georgian, which is published in 2012 by International Black Sea University. My latest research focuses on comparative politics, the alliance of civilizations and conflict resolution for global problems. (Analysis of International Conflicts and Possible Solution, Methods Using Fuzzy Logic as an Alternative Perspective) In particular I have been working on the inherent conflicts of political and cultural domination.

LANGUAGES

English Full professional proficiency

Turkish Native proficiency

Georgian Full professional proficiency